<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Gods gracious thoughts tovvards great sinners.</title>
            <author>Homes, Nathanael, 1599-1678.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 101 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A74767</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E385_22</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201472</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861977</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861977</idno>
            <idno type="VID">114123</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A74767)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 114123)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 61:E385[22])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Gods gracious thoughts tovvards great sinners.</title>
                  <author>Homes, Nathanael, 1599-1678.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Matthew Simmons, dwelling in Aldersgate-street.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London; :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Nathaniel Homes, whose name appears at the head of the preface, and whose initials appear at the end.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May 4th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Salvation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sin --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:114123:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:114123:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>GODS GRACIOUS THOUGHTS TOVVARDS GREAT <hi>SINNERS.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>JER. 29.11.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>But I know the thoughts I thinke towards you, ſaith the Lord, thoughts of peace, and not of evill, to give you an expected end.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>EPHES. 3.19.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The love of Chriſt paſſeth knowledge.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON;</hi> Printed by <hi>Matthew Simmons,</hi> dwelling in <hi>Alderſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate</hi>-ſtreet. 1647.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:114123:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:114123:2"/>
            <head>NATHANAEL HOMES, TO THE CHURCH IN FELLOWSHIP WITH HIM.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Eare Brethren and Siſters, as my compaſsions to ſome bleeding hearts among you, did put me upon this diſcourſe, in our more pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate weekly meeting; ſo their unexpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted importunitie, for Copies, have ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsitated me to print it, ſo as it was, ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly compiled, and ruggedly delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, unpoliſhed, and untrimmed for pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like view of all abroad. But being wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling you ſhould have it, I would rather deny mine own honour, then you of any ſpirituall comfort I might hold forth to you, who am yours in the Lord by many ſtrong obligations.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>N. H.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my ſtudy in</hi> Mary Staynings.
<date>
                     <hi>Decem. 2. 1646.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:114123:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:114123:3"/>
            <div type="part">
               <head>GODS GRACIOUS THOUGHTS TOWARDS GREAT SINNERS.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>ISAIAH 55.8, 9.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>For my thoughts are not your thoughts, neither are your wayes my wayes, ſaith the Lord.</p>
                     <p>For as the heavens are higher then the earth, ſo are my wayes higher then your wayes, and my thoughts then your thoughts.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He former part of this Chapter is a moſt glorious invitation of poore ſinners to free mercy, <hi>verſ.</hi> 1. to the end of the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> verſe, in which 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> verſe the Lord tells all <hi>commers</hi> to him, that he hath mercy for them, and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy with eminency; namely, that <hi>He will have mercy on them: And he will abundantly pardon.</hi> Or, as it is neerer to the Hebrew, and is ſo expreſſed in the Margin of your Bibles; <hi>He will multiply to pardon,</hi> or, <hi>Multiply pardons.</hi> The freeneſſe, fulneſſe, and faithfulneſſe of this glorious grace and favour, the Lord moſt ſtrongly demonſtrates, to confute all doubtings, and chaſe away all feares that are in the hearts of drooping ſinners, in the verſes of the Text. The <hi>Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrophe</hi> and upſhot of all is this; That the Lord having removed their ſinnes, he will remove their judgements, and change their ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes into joyes, <hi>verſ.</hi> 12, 13. The ſubſtance of the verſes of the Text in the ſenſe of them, are the <hi>matter</hi> of the <hi>Demonſtration;</hi> The coherence or inference of them in the ſeverall <hi>FORS,</hi> are the <hi>forme,</hi> that forme them into arguments, to remove their doubts and feare<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:114123:4"/>
As if the Lord ſhould ſay; <q>When I ſay, I will have mercy, and abounding, or multiplyed pardoning mercy; you ought not to doubt of it, or feare; <hi>FOR my thoughts are not your thoughts,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>FOR as the heavens are higher then the earth, ſo are my thoughts higher then your thoughts. FOR as the raine comes down from heaven,</hi> &amp;c. So that one <hi>FOR</hi> backs another.</q> And then ſaith the Lord, Your ſins being done away, your judgements ſhall be removed. <hi>Ver.</hi> 12, 13. <hi>FOR you ſhall goe out with joy,</hi> &amp;c. You ſhall by the effect of remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of your ſorrowes, diſcerne the cauſe, <hi>viz.</hi> the pardoning of your ſinnes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Doctrine.</note>Out of all, for the deſigne in hand, I picke and cull this one Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; That the incomparableneſſe of Gods gracious thoughts to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards poore ſinners, above and beyond their thoughts, is ſufficient to ſtop the mouth of all objections, and ſtill the cryes of all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections in all their miſeries.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Note (for explanation of this rich Doctrine) that our miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries are twofold. Afflictions; Tranſgreſſions. Thoſe the threed, theſe the needle. For theſe are they that prick and ſting to the quick. Theſe the ſting in the mouth or tayle of afflictions. <hi>The ſting of death is ſinne,</hi> 1 Cor. 15. A confluence of all afflictions of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves cannot ſting ſo, as the ſingle eſſence of the ſinne when God will ſet it on the conſcience. <hi>Pauls concupiſcence</hi> ſtings him more, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. then his <hi>being killed all the day long,</hi> Rom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Afflictions whip the body, ſinne the ſoule. <hi>The ſpirit of a man</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon) may ſuſtaine his infirmities; But a wounded ſpirit who can heare?</hi> That is, of himſelfe without Gods grace.</p>
               <p>Now ſecondly obſerve, that in all theſe afflictions and ſinnes, Gods thoughts towards us poore ſinners, are ſuch as are incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable and tranſcendent, above and beyond that wee can thinke: 1. Father with <hi>ſimple cogitation;</hi> That is, we cannot thinke towards others in the like caſe of miſery, as God thinkes towards us in the ſame caſe. 2. Or with <hi>reflexive comprehenſion,</hi> or <hi>apprehenſion,</hi> that in, to conceive what thoſe thoughts of God are towards us in our miſery, juſt as he thinkes them. Both theſe ſeeme to be cleerly, in the Text. For the firſt, <q>I can, ſaith the Lord; <hi>ſhew mercy</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever there is a ſence of miſery, though that miſery did as well provoke me by the ſin of it, as it did grieve man with the afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:114123:4"/>For my thoughts are not your thoughts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the ſecond. If there be abundance of ſinnes bringing abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance "of iudgements, <q>I can (ſaith the Lord) <hi>abundantly</hi> pardon; <hi>For my thoughts are above your thoughts.</hi>
                  </q> As if the Lord ſhould ſay of the firſt, thus; <q>Can you have ſuch thoughts of mercy on miſery as I can? eſpecially where you are provoked? Doe not you uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally repell violence with violence? Doe you not uſe to render evill for evill? Are you not uſually for the punitive way? Or if you paſſe by a few wrongs, can you paſſe by <hi>abundance?</hi> Doe you not cry againſt multiplying of offences, <hi>Immedicabile vulnus,</hi> &amp;c. cut the putrifying limbe off? Doe you not after once or twice warning, fall to harming? Do not your Magiſtrates burne in the hand, then hang up the neck?</q> And you admoniſh, then puniſh. But I can thinke thoughts of mercy, contrary to all theſe, as hath been ſhewed in the Text.</p>
               <p>For the ſecond.</p>
               <q>
                  <p>You (as if the Lord ſhould ſay) can hardly thinke that I can thus thinke, but I can. <hi>For my thoughts are above yours;</hi> You are men, I a God; you corrupt, I pure, I prove it thus: Doe you ſee the diſproportion of creatures, of the Heavens above the earth? Much more between an infinit Creator &amp; the creature. Can you take the juſt altitude of the Heavens above the Earth? Then note how high my thoughts are above yours. Therefore theſe my thoughts I propound and preſſe to huſh and ſtop the mouth of all objections, and ſtill your ſorrowing, fearing, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining-dejections.</p>
                  <p>If you object any crooked unworthy thing to diſparage my thoughts, and ſo to prejudice your ſelves in laying hold on my thoughts, let the anſwer be, my <hi>thoughts not as yours.</hi> Mine in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance are all good, right, &amp;c. As my <hi>words</hi> are, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19. ſo are my <hi>thoughts.</hi> No evill, no iniquitie, no crueltie in my thoughts. If you thinke any, you bring it with you, you can finde none in me: you goe about to pervert the ſtraight wayes and thoughts of the Lord, <hi>Act.</hi> 13.10. But the Lords thoughts are like him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; The Lords thoughts and wayes are equall, they are yours that are unequall, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.25. As if the Lord ſhould ſay, take it for a generall rule, <hi>What ever your thoughts are, if they be not moſt juſt, good, holy,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>they are not mine.</hi> But you may object, you think your thoughts are ſo; Therefore take this for another gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:114123:5"/>
rule; <hi>That whatſoever thoughts doe not tend to your ſalvation,</hi> tend to bring you towards mee, according to the deſigne of this Text, and <hi>word of mine, thoſe thoughts are not my thoughts,</hi> Ezek. 18. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33. If you object, ſecondly, that yee cannot imagine how I can have ſuch thoughts of mercy to ſuch ſinners as you are; The anſwer is, As the Heavens are diſtant and different from the Earth, ſo are my thoughts above yours. The Heavens are ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the Earth, that the Earth with all its Cedars, miſts, clouds, fiery meteors, cannot reach it; ſo nor can your thoughts in a rationall way reach mine. And as the Heavens are greater, ſo my thoughts, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.17. And as the Heavens are bigger then the Earth, ſo my thoughts are like my ſelfe, infinite. And as the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens are more glorious then the Earth; ſo are my thoughts then yours: And as the Heavens give light, ſo doe my thoughts to yours. And as the Heavens ſhine on the bad as well as good, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.45. ſo doe my thoughts on ſinners as well as on Saints. If you object, thirdly, that though theſe are effectuall expreſſions in themſelves, able to doe much, yet they do not take, affect your ſoules. The anſwer is, that as the operations of the Heavens, in drawing up miſts, and powring them downe in raine, doe the worke, the raine returnes not in vaine; ſo ſhall my word be, that expreſſeth my thoughts; If the heavens do not ſhine, raine, rowle, raiſe the Sunne, &amp;c. in vaine, but cauſe ſpring, harveſt, &amp;c. then ſure my thoughts ſhining and dropping in my words, ſhall not be in vaine. If as the earth waites on the heavens; ſo you waite, ſeed-time, ſpring-time, harveſt-time will come. My thoughts ſhall take hold of your thoughts, and overcome them, and transforme them into mine: your thoughts ſhall truſt in my thoughts of truth: your thoughts ſhall hope in my thoughts of mercy; your thoughts ſhall rejoyce in my thoughts of love; your thoughts ſhall reſt quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in my thoughts of peace; that all your ſins are pardoned, and ſo your judgements ſhall be done away, at leaſt as judgements.</p>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſefull is this,</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. To put us upon the conſideration of Gods thoughts, ſo farre as we are able by enlightened reaſon: 1. How different in kinde our thoughts are from Gods thoughts. 2. How diſtant and ſhort in degree our thoughts are below Gods thoughts, when we ſet about to apprehend them. Both theſe are in the Text, and Doctrine, as we ſaid; compare <hi>Jerem.</hi> 29.11.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:114123:5"/>1. For the difference in kinde.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Our thoughts cannot be <hi>firſt</hi> towards God, in the buſineſſe of our ſalvation, our thoughts cannot be the firſt-mover. For na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally, <hi>our thoughts and imaginations are onely evill continually,</hi> Gen. 6.5. Wee are borne wild Aſſes Colis, <hi>Job</hi> 11.12. <hi>Wee goe aſtray as ſoone as wee are borne:</hi> but Gods thoughts are <hi>firſt</hi> in our ſalvation; <hi>He</hi> (ſaith the Pſalmiſt) <hi>underſtandeth our thoughts afarre off,</hi> or <hi>long before.</hi> Therefore his thoughts are precedent to ours. He here in the 6, and 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> verſes before the Text, makes the firſt motion about our ſalvation; and as it is in 1 <hi>Job.</hi> 4.19. <hi>We love him, becauſe he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved us firſt;</hi> and therefore his thoughts firſt move ours. His love firſt ſounds forth; then our love is as the Eccho. He firſt allureth, then we are drawn. A mighty Comfort; that his thoughts being firſt towards us; their graciouſneſſe muſt needs be free. Though wee cannot glory in our thoughts, as preventing, or perſwaſive of Gods thoughts, yet we may glory in this greater thing, that Gods thoughts anticipate, prevent, and perſwade our thoughts. <hi>Acti agi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> wee in every thought and deed act not, but as we are acted by God. Gods thoughts are the Originall, ours but the Copy.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Our thoughts are not kinde thoughts, ſweet thoughts to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; we are ſelfe-lovers: the originall ſin of the world. See <hi>Adam.</hi> Doe wee thinke thoughts of love to our enemies? Eſpecially un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſought unto? Much leſſe would we prompt them to ſeeke unto us, that we might ſhew them kindneſſe. Would their miſery be our pitie? Would it not be our joy rather? So uncharitable is nature, <hi>that we rejoyce in iniquitie.</hi> But God hath all the contrary thoughts to theſe.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Our thoughts are limited thoughts, we cannot pitie or par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don (if we doe either) much or many. Wee ſay, <hi>how oft,</hi> Mat. 18.21. Wee are ready to ſtudy an end, afore wee begin. But Gods thoughts of mercy, are <hi>abounding</hi> thoughts, and <hi>multiplying</hi> thoughts; thoughts of <hi>abounding mercy,</hi> and <hi>multiplying mercies and pardons.</hi> He ſhews mercy to thouſands of generations, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. and therefore to thouſands of ſinnes of one ſoule. <hi>He heales backſlidings,</hi> Hoſ. 14. Obſerve the indefinite expreſſion. And the Pſalmiſt ſpeaks of <hi>a multitude of mercies,</hi> Pſal. 5.7. Pſal. 100.7. <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſpeakes of <hi>multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of loving kindneſſes,</hi> Iſa. 63.7. And <hi>Jeremy</hi> ſaith, <hi>There is no fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of his mercy, ſo we are not confirmed.</hi> How much and how many
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:114123:6"/>
evills did he pardon in <hi>Manaſſeh, Magdalen, Saul?</hi> How many backſlidings in <hi>Peter,</hi> and much more in <hi>Solomon?</hi> I may ſay to a true beleever, as he doth not make an end of ſinning, ſo God can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not make an end of pardoning. But then as his pardoning takes off our feare of ſinne; ſo it takes off our love of ſinne. His good will takes off our ill wills, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Our thoughts at beſt have much reluctation againſt good, and ordinarily much evill in them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. But Gods thoughts are all good, altogether good, purely and perfectly good, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning our good, to cure us of our evill, and to fill us with good, <hi>Jer.</hi> 29.11. So it is ſaid, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. <hi>God is good,</hi> and doth good.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Our thoughts, when not vile, are vaine, <hi>Jer.</hi> 4.14. But Gods thoughts are great and maine thoughts, touching the great things of our ſalvation.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Our thoughts are of contentions with men, and of tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion againſt God, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.7. But Gods are of peace and reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. So argued in Text, and <hi>Jer.</hi> 29.11. He is the God of all peace, and ſutable are his thoughts.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Our thoughts are craving begging thoughts, we are all up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the getting hand, of man by intreating, of God by praying; wee are more in prayer then in praiſe. But Gods thoughts are giving thoughts, bountifull thoughts, thoughts of giving afore our asking, and more then many times we dare aske; ſo before and in the Text. And <hi>Jer.</hi> 29.11. when they are deſpairing, he would be giving. <hi>I am found of them that ſought me not,</hi> Iſai. 65.1. God gave more to <hi>Paul</hi> then he thought on, <hi>Acts</hi> 9. and compare 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. Yea <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> had more then he asked. So the promiſe is, <hi>Seeke firſt the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God.</hi> We aske oft to <hi>beleeve,</hi> he gives more, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.29. We aske oft to <hi>overcome</hi> ſuch or ſuch a thing, ſuch a ſinne; but in that God gives us to overcome many other ſinnes. Thus is it moſt true, that <hi>it is a more bleſſed thing to give then to receive.</hi> God bleſſed for evermore gives. And we could not be ever asking, but that God is never weary of giving. Many more particulars might be given of the different kinds of our thoughts from Gods, but theſe are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to enlarge our meditation.</p>
               <p n="8">8. When we turne about our thoughts to underſtand the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable thoughts of God towards us, our thoughts are at a diſtance, fall infinitely ſhort of comprehending them as we ſhould.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:114123:6"/>
Therefore God ſaith in the Text, <hi>My thoughts are above your thoughts.</hi> And <hi>Jerem.</hi> 29.11. <hi>I know my own thoughts,</hi> though you doe not as you ought, I doe, <hi>that they are thoughts of peace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As Gods thoughts are in regard of <hi>matter,</hi> namely, mercy, good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, pardonings, ſo in <hi>meaſure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Infinite.</hi> Pſal. 92.5. <hi>O Lord, how great are thy workes, thy thoughts are very deepe.</hi> Anſwerable to 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.10. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>The deep things of God;</hi> whereby to ſhelter us from the <hi>depths of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan,</hi> Revel. 2.24. that is, ſinne, ſinfull temptations, ſtratagems, &amp;c. <hi>Gods underſtanding is infinite,</hi> Pſal. 147.5. The Apoſtle makes an heavenly exclamation, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.33. <hi>O the depth of the riches both of the wiſdome and knowledge of God, how unſearchable are his judgements,</hi> diſcernings or determinations, <hi>and his wayes paſt finding out!</hi> God hath thoughts of mercy for millions of ſinners, therefore ſure enough for all the ſinnes of one ſinner.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Continuall;</hi> continued without interruption, ſo that as they have no beginning, nor ending, ſo no breakings off in the middle, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Certaine,</hi> firme, eſtabliſhed; ſo before the Text; <hi>The ſure mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of David;</hi> That is, promiſed to <hi>David;</hi> that is made over to us in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>David.</hi> That as ſure as <hi>Chriſt</hi> is in our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſo wee are one with him by faith. Chriſt is the great <hi>pledge,</hi> or <hi>witneſſe,</hi> in verſe 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> before the Text, of Gods mercifull thoughts towards us poore ſinners. So that if we be unlovely in our ſelves, yet we are <hi>acceptable</hi> and <hi>well-pleaſing</hi> to <hi>God</hi> in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> Mat. 3. laſt, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.3.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Immutable,</hi> both in kinde and degree. They cannot be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, or leſſe then ever they have been, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.19. And <hi>James</hi> ſaith, <hi>With him is no ſhadow of change.</hi> Yea God in Chriſt the ſame for ever, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Intuitive.</hi> God thinks all his thoughts at once. As a mans eye ſees all it ſees at that looke, in one twinkling of an eye, ſo God ſees all abſolutely that ever were, are, or ſhall be at once. He needs not any rationall intellectuall diſcourſe to goe from one thing to another in his thoughts, but he can &amp; doth comprehend all at once.</p>
               <p>Now upon theſe and the like properties of Gods thoughts, wee fall very ſhort of and below a due apprehenſion of Gods thoughts; and fall to doubting, becauſe in oppoſition,</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:114123:7"/>1. To the <hi>infinitneſſe</hi> of God thoughts, our thoughts are <hi>finite;</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> eye, nor the Sonne it ſelfe can behold all the world in its com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat roundneſſe; much leſſe can our finite thoughts reach Gods infinite thoughts.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To the <hi>continuitie</hi> of Gods thoughts, ours are <hi>interrupted,</hi> broken off oft-times in the middle. Many by-thoughts intervene between our moſt ſerious thoughts, whiles they are riſing up to any conſiderable height of apprehenſion of Gods thoughts, or of any thing that is good; and ſo they diſturbe and diſſipate our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipts of minde.</p>
               <p n="3">3. To the <hi>certainty</hi> of his thoughts, our thoughts are moſt <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain</hi> thoughts. Sometimes they are rather conjectures then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves, rather opinions then judgements, rather diſputings then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminations. And ſo (as the weakneſſe of our eye to behold the fixed ſtarres at ſuch a diſtance, makes us thinke they twinckle, when as it is the quavering of our weake eye) our <hi>uncertainty</hi> in thinking makes us think Gods thoughts are <hi>uncertaine,</hi> when as it is the uncertaintie and variableneſſe of our thoughts.</p>
               <p n="4">4. To the <hi>immutabilitie</hi> of Gods thoughts, ſtands in oppoſition the <hi>mutabilitie</hi> of our thoughts. Sometimes they are on God, ſometimes off, and on the creature. And when on God, ſometimes ſtronger, ſometimes weaker, ſometimes almoſt nothing. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times they catch one thing, and let that goe, and then catch ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſo loſe the ſeries, method, and dependance of things, to finde out the excellency of Gods thoughts.</p>
               <p n="5">5. To the <hi>intuitiveneſſe</hi> of Gods thoughts, ſtands oppoſit the <hi>diſcurſiveneſſe</hi> of our thoughts. For being we are faine to know by diſcourſe from one thing to another, in a rationall way, as from the effect to the cauſe, &amp;c. And our reaſon is imperfect, and our <hi>knowledge is but in part;</hi> wee muſt needs oft-times fall very low in apprehending ordinary things, much more in diving into extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary things. Wee cannot alwayes by the utmoſt compaſſe of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, reach to the formes of ſome naturall things; how then can our diſcurive, reach Gods intuitive thoughts?</p>
               <p>Now therefore ſaith the Lord in the Text, when yee heare mee ſpeake of ſuch high things as are here mentioned; <q>As, <hi>I will abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly pardon,</hi> &amp;c. you wonder at them, but doe not notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding doubt of them, or diſpute againſt them; For my
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:114123:7"/>
thoughts are known to mee, (<hi>Jer.</hi> 29.11.) they are not ſo meane and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ow as yours, but <hi>farre above,</hi> (as in this 55. of <hi>Iſaiah</hi>) and therefore admire, but not deſpaire. <hi>They are above your thoughts or high as the Heavens are above the Earth.</hi> But I can tell the alti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of mine own thoughts, I think of <hi>mercy,</hi> and of <hi>multiplying pardons.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe two places, the Text, and <hi>Jer.</hi> 29.11. hold forth theſe particulars.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <q>1. (As if the Lord ſhould ſay) nor you nor any man elſe, no nor Angels (which are enquirers into the Goſpel, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.12.) can tell my thoughts ſo well as I my ſelfe. <hi>Fleſh and bloud</hi> could not <hi>reveale</hi> to <hi>Peter</hi> the things of Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.17. And in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. The <hi>naturall man receiveth not the things of God, becauſe ſpiritually diſcerned.</hi> No nor can your ſpirituall minds compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the full of things, for yee <hi>know in part,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. As the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions (Mich.</hi> 4.12.) <hi>know not my thoughts, nor underſtand my coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell</hi> concerning you, ſo you may labour to know them, but ſtill they will <hi>paſſe your knowledge,</hi> Epheſ. 3.19. The loving thoughts of my heart are rather <hi>felt,</hi> then <hi>underſtood,</hi> Rom. 5. <hi>I ſhed my love into your hearts.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <q>2. That I, even I my ſelfe doe know all mine own thoughts per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly, how high ſoever they be, I comprehend them all. They are all diſtinctly and fairly written in my heart, and I can read and compute, and ſcan every one of them to a tittle, and ſettle them in an unalterable way, by an unchangeable decree.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <q>3. That I acknowledge my thoughts, to be high thoughts of love, mercy, &amp;c. ſo as I cannot keepe them to my ſelfe, but doe ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them, and in order of times, and of your neceſſities do explaine them to you, though you cannot reach to the utmoſt height of them. I make them legible to your eyes in my booke; and I make them frequently to ſound in your eares in the miniſtrie of my Word; and I give you a repreſentation of them in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to many of your ſenſes; But though you cannot compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend them fully as they are in their infiniteneſſe every way; yet by that you apprehend, yee may admire the reſt, as perfectly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite, and incomprehenſible. As the Heavens and Earth will be ſeene of us but in the Hemiſphere, yet you conclude they are round.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:114123:8"/>
                  <q>4. That though your thoughts have many objections againſt my thoughts, yet I know my thoughts will anſwer all the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections of your thoughts. Diſpute and try.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="1">
                  <q>1. It may be you poore ſinners will ſay, you have had ſuch deep apprehenſions of your ſinnes, and ſuch long inward conflicts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout them, that you ſay in your hearts, and thinke you ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee good day more.</q>
               </p>
               <p>But my thoughts anſwer you out of theſe Texts, that <q>
                     <hi>my thoughts are thoughts of mercy, of multiplying pardons, and that above your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion. Thoughts of peace,</hi> I think peace towards you, as I am the God of peace. And I have many thoughts about it, and great thoughts like my ſelfe. For they are <hi>my thoughts.</hi> And though little man doth aſſay to imagine great things, yet your thoughts are not like my thoughts.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. It may be, you will object againe, <q>That your thoughts thinke my thoughts are not ſuch thoughts of mercy,  Becauſe my hand hath been upon you to afflict you;</q> and perhaps the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, or its ſmart is not yet off from you; and therefore that I ſtill intend to have ſevere thoughts towards you. But my thoughts are as in theſe Texts, and the Contexts that lead to and follow them, that is; <q>That whereas you can be alwayes angry, and irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concileably angry with men; fleſh and bloud is prone to be <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mercifull</hi> and <hi>implacable;</hi>
                  </q> my thoughts are not ſuch; for my thoughts cannot be like yours, they muſt be <hi>better,</hi> and <hi>above</hi> yours, or they cannot be my thoughts; I tell you plainly in theſe Texts, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 55. <hi>Let him that hath nothing come and buy,</hi> ver. 1. That <hi>there is a time when I will be found,</hi> ver. 6. And the <hi>preſent time</hi> when I offer grace and favour, is the accepted time, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.2. Even as he did heare Chriſt Jeſus, that was made ſinne for us; ſo he heares ſinners. And as there is a time when I ſpake to thee ſinner, to cauſe thee to leave ſin; ſo then do I intend to lay aſide my wrath, <hi>ver.</hi> 7. before the Text. So that my thoughts of anger are <hi>but for a time,</hi> but my thoughts of mercy are everlaſting, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 30.5. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.28. &amp;c. He hath regard to his <hi>Oath</hi> there. He hath not ſworn to be angry with ſinners for ever, but hath ſworn to have mercy. And accordingly he doth affirme, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 54.7. the next Chapter afore the Text. You the ſonnes of men cannot tell when to lay aſide your thoughts of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, till they degenerate into malice; but I can ſee my time. Yea
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:114123:8"/>
though I afflict my people ſo yours, yet I can have thoughts of peace to them at laſt, <hi>Jer.</hi> 29.11. Yea all that while reſolve on them. Yea whiles I am afflicting, I have thoughts of love, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. And therefore ſaith the Lord, <hi>My ſonne be not weary of the Lords chaſtiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> Pro. 3.11, 12. But doe as <hi>Iſai.</hi> 8.17.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It may be you poore ſinners will object, that your thoughts are not able to beare the lying upon you of your ſorrowes of ſinnes and afflictions. Therefore you would have them removed. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore alſo my thoughts anſwer you thus: I have, as in this Text, all manner and meaſure of mercies, to take away the perplexity of your ſpirits. And beſides I have entailed on my pardoning mercy, afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on removing mercy. So <hi>ver.</hi> 12. after the Text.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It may be, your thoughts will object; But our perplexities and miſeries have been ſo many and long, that wee are exceeding thirſty, our appetites are enlarged, wee thinke wee can have never enough of God, and his preſence, and comfort. My thoughts ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt in the Text, and elſwhere, anſwer this ſufficiently, that I have <hi>abundance of mercy for you, multiplyed mercy;</hi> Yea ſo much as your thoughts cannot reach unto. And it ſhall ſatiate you, as the raine doth the earth; and not onely you ſhall joy, but the world ſhall ſeeme before you to ſing, and to be full of joy; ſo from the Text to <hi>verſ.</hi> 13.</p>
               <p n="5">5. But yet may be your thoughts object, that ſome of you have waited a long while for a good houre, and have not yet attained it. The Lords thoughts anſwer this too. His thoughts are not as our thoughts, that is, they ſhall not ſtay too long as we think, ere they ſend comfort. But as the Heavens are above the Earth, yet in due time water it. So &amp;c. And <hi>Jer.</hi> 29.11. you ſhall have your expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. Hope is not aſhamed at laſt, yea not aſhamed whiles it waites, becauſe <hi>the love of God is ſhed abroad in our hearts,</hi> Hab. 2 3, 4.</p>
               <p>Thus farre of the firſt uſe, of putting us upon the conſideration of Gods incomparable thoughts, to ſee how farre they prevent all objections.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Is to put us upon the exerciſe of our faith, about the unparal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leld thoughts of God; That where our beſt thoughts fall ſhort, there the faith that Chriſt hath given us may aſcend. And indeed if Gods thoughts are farre above our thoughts, then it is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:114123:9"/>
worke of faith to take the tranſcendency of them into the view of it: As thus.</p>
               <p n="1">1. To beleeve the originall and inuate conception of theſe thoughts of grace and favour to poore ſinners. They ſpring meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from the ſweet, good, and unſpeakable excellency of Gods na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: deſcribed <hi>Exod.</hi> 34. Compare <hi>Iſai.</hi> 43.25. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. Thou art good, and thou doeſt good. Therefore it ſuppoſeth, he is good, and thinketh good. So notably <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.5. His thoughts doe ariſe from his <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, his moſt gracious diſpoſition. As out of the evill nature of man, proceeds all evill thoughts, Adulteries, murthers, thefts, &amp;c. So contrary. This well applyed by faith anſwers the objection of our unworthineſſe. For as there was no good in us when God firſt thought of us to move him to thinke on us; for ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he looked on us as <hi>nothing,</hi> or as a moſt <hi>ſinfull ſomething;</hi> to no unworthineſſe, either of our <hi>nothingneſſe,</hi> or <hi>ſinfulneſſe,</hi> could hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him from his gracious thoughts towards us. As it is ſaid, <hi>He will have mercy on whom he will have mercy;</hi> ſo he will <hi>thinke what be will thinke of grace and favour</hi> to poore ſinners, nothing can helpe, nothing ſhall hinder him. As God cannot be otherwiſe in his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture then he is, ſo he cannot be otherwiſe in his gracious thoughts, then what he will thinke.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> But God hath a pure nature, and a juſt nature, &amp;c. And therefore from thence by the ſame proportion muſt ariſe thoughts of hating impure ſinne, and of puniſhing unrighteous ſinne; with which by nature we abound.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. This doth not contradict Gods thoughts of grace and favour to grievous ſinners, becauſe God was pure and juſt, when from all eternitie, foreſeeing all things, he had thoſe thoughts of grace and favour.</p>
               <p n="2">2. God is pleaſed to propoſe to us his Juſtice, <hi>conditionally,</hi> upon our obſtinacy againſt mercy. So all along the Scripture. But holds forth his offer of mercy <hi>abſolutely,</hi> without any condition of ours, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 55.1. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 43.25. <hi>Revel.</hi> 22.17. If at any time there be any ſound of a condition, it is one of his own making, and in-making in us, ſubordinate, not oppoſit to free grace, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.8. And he that thinks to ſave, thinks to give faith.</p>
               <p n="3">3. God is pleaſed to ſignifie to us, that he loves to have his <hi>mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy rejoyce over his juſtice,</hi> Jam. 2.13. Grace <hi>glorieth.</hi> It is the glory of Gods mercy, that it preventeth judgement.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:114123:9"/>4. In that God hates ſinne, and hath juſtice to puniſh it, he hath provided a Saviour to remove the guilt and filth of ſinne, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. laſt ſave one. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. laſt. He made Chriſt (taking our nature upon him, and ſanctifying it, and making atonement in it) <hi>to be ſin for us, that we might be made the righteouſneſſe of God.</hi> On him <hi>he laid the iniquities of us all,</hi> Iſai. 53. And on us <hi>he laid the righteouſneſſe of God,</hi> 2 Cor. 5. laſt. The righteouſneſſe of God, therefore good e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, to be acceptable to himſelfe, and great enough, being infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, to appeaſe him for the finite unrighteouſneſſe of man.</p>
               <p n="5">5. And laſtly, God doth love to dignifie the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> above the firſt, yea to make Chriſt the plaiſter more ſoveraigne then <hi>Adam</hi> the ſoare can be malignant, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. It's the buſineſſe of thoſe two Chapters. The upſhot of all is ſet down in golden Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. Two laſt verſes; <hi>Where ſinne abounded, grace did much more abound. That as ſinne hath reigned unto death, ſo might grace REIGNE</hi> (mark the phraſe) <hi>through righteouſneſſe unto eternall life by Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi> By which it appeares, that as heretofore ſin did <hi>reigne over us,</hi> ſo now Gods gracious favour through Chriſts righteouſneſſe ſhould <hi>reigne</hi> over our ſinnes. And that the benefit might be imparted to poore ſinners abounding with ſinne, God would make his grace of favour much more to abound. Of which ſee more in that glorious Scripture, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.14.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Exerciſe faith upon the birth of theſe thoughts of mercy; Namely, that as they are conceived from Gods moſt excellent ſweet nature; ſo they are brought to the birth of a gracious predeſtinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, appointment, purpoſe, or chooſing. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.29. <hi>Whom he did fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>know</hi> (out of thoſe thoughts of mercy that were conceived in his ſweet nature) <hi>he did predeſtinate and appoint.</hi> What to doe, or be? <hi>To be made conformable to his Sonne Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> They ſhould be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their capacitie, in no worſe condition then his Sonne Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.3, 4, 5. <hi>Hath bleſſed us with all ſpirituall bleſſings in heavenly places, or things, in Chriſt. According as he hath choſen us in him before the foundation of the world, having predeſtinated us unto the Adoption of children by Jeſus Chriſt to himſelfe, according to the good pleaſure of his will.</hi> See here the good will of God is the riſe of predeſtination; and predeſtination is the riſe of chooſing: of purpoſe, ſee preſently. Thoſe purpoſes of God are free, unconſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, unneceſſitated, they ariſe out of his own free nature and good
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:114123:10"/>
will, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.11. <hi>In whom</hi> (that is in Chriſt) <hi>wee have obtained an inheritance, being predetion did according to the purpoſe of him that worketh all things according to the Counſell of his own will.</hi> Obſerve, he ſaith not, <hi>according to the Counſell of his underſtanding.</hi> As if he would know, find, and conſider ſomething in us. But <hi>according to the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of his own will.</hi> His good will and ſweet inclination to poore ſinners, is that which puts forth theſe thoughts of grace, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour. So that as in <hi>Iſai.</hi> 43.25. He aſſures us that as he can love him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; ſo he <hi>can blot out ſinnes;</hi> So here he doth warrant us, that as he cannot be of another nature, but (as the Angel ſang) <hi>Good will to men;</hi> he is of a ſweet and mercifull diſpoſition; ſo he purpoſeth ſalvation to poore ſinners.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Theſe purpoſes of favour are unmoveable, and unchangeable, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.19. <hi>Nevertheleſſe</hi> (though falſe-hearted <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Philetus</hi> fall off) <hi>the foundation of God ſtandeth ſure, having this ſeale, The Lord knoweth who are his.</hi> So that againſt all feares of change, this becomes an aſſurance; that <hi>whom he loves, he loves to the end, Joh.</hi> 13.1. <hi>With him</hi> (ſaith <hi>James) is no ſhadow of changeing.</hi> And this ſecond particular, (the birth of Gods gracious thoughts, with the properties) anſwers many objections that might ariſe. For God is not unreſolved to ſave them whom he loves in his everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoughts; as a man is unreſolved oft times whether to have her whom he loves. God is unmoveable from his purpoſes of mercy by any thing that is in us or from us.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> But in Gods purpoſe and predeſtination lyes alſo his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation: and that breeds doubts and feares in us.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. It is true, that when God electeth ſome, conſequently he paſſeth by others. But this preterition, paſſing by, or non-electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, doth onely leave men to ſhift for themſelves; it doth not paſſe any condemnation upon them that are omitted. For it were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt with God, to our underſtanding, to purpoſe to condemne his creature, without an eye, and relation to ſome wrong the creature ſhould doe him. So that it is ſome other thought beyond that of <hi>paſſing</hi> by, that reprobates, which wee call <hi>predamnation,</hi> or <hi>fore-condemning.</hi> Which is, that God foreſeeing any man to ſinne ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinately and perpetually againſt the means of grace offered to him, on him God puts forth a purpoſe of condemning him. God doth elect freely, becauſe we cannot doe the leaſt imperfect good, as all is
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:114123:10"/>
imperfect, but from the gift and power of Gods goodneſſe. But reprobation is for the deſert of ſinne, becauſe wee can (as <hi>Adam</hi> did) moſt freely and fully ſinne of our ſelves. A Magiſtrate rewards ſome ſubjects <hi>freely,</hi> though they have done ſome good. For they had their life, livelihood, education, &amp;c. under their good govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to doe that good. And the good it ſelfe is a ſufficient <hi>allure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> vertue being lovely enough in it ſelfe; and a ſufficient <hi>reward</hi> of it ſelfe, every vertue yeelding at leaſt a certain Inward <hi>quietation of minde</hi> (as the Heathen Philoſopher confeſſeth) as alſo an <hi>out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward honour</hi> among Civill honeſt men; and therefore <hi>Honor dicitur ab honeſtate.</hi> Honour hath its derivation, of name, and thing, from honeſty. But the Magiſtrate cannot with any juſtice condemne or puniſh any Subject, nor have a purpoſe ſo to doe, but as he hath an eye upon, and evidence of that mans tranſgreſſing. By the ſame pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion, with infinite more exactneſſe, God doth purpoſe, and elect to ſalvation freely, but cannot purpoſe to reprobate any to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, but upon ſure evidence that ſuch will ſinne impenitent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, againſt the meanes of grace, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 36.11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16. <hi>Pro.</hi> 29.1. But you will ſay, that Gods <hi>paſſing by</hi> thoſe that are not elected, doth put a neceſſitie that they cannot be ſaved. We anſwer, it puts a neceſſitie in God of <hi>infallibilitie,</hi> that he cannot be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; but not a neceſſitie of <hi>conſtraint</hi> on men to force them to ſinne. As the Angels full of glory, did moſt voluntarily ſin in Heaven, ſo did <hi>Adam</hi> full of goodneſſe, moſt freely ſin in Paradiſe; and ſo doe wee now in the world. God doth not reprobate, becauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ee may be ſure to ſinne; but becauſe he ſees we are ſure to ſinne, therefore he doth reprobate with <hi>predamnation.</hi> And therefore notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his eternall thoughts of <hi>predamnation,</hi> he allowes every man ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient outward meanes &amp; inward light to underſtand thoſe means before he doth actually damne them in hell. So in the ſaid 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 36. <hi>Pro.</hi> 29.</p>
               <p>Our ſecond anſwer is this; That predeſtination is a long golden chaine, impregnable, inſeparable, that not the leaſt linck can be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken off. So <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.29, 30. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.3, 4, 5, 6. to the end of 12. <hi>per. &amp;</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.19. So that if we ſee but the leaſt and laſt linck faſtened to our hearts, as to <hi>ſanctifie</hi> us, or to make us <hi>unfeignedly call in his Name,</hi> or ſincerely deſire and endeavour <hi>to depart from iniquitie;</hi> you may be ſure that the other end of the chaine is faſtened to God, heart, by eternall election.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:114123:11"/>Third anſwer, Conſider in thoſe places of <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1. Gods de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ee relates firſt in order to Chriſt, and as it were paſſeth through him; ſo that as we looke on Chriſt, and behave out ſelves towards Chriſt, to receive him, or refuſe him; ſo wee may conclude of our predeſtination. Thus of the birth of Gods thoughts.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The life and actings of thoſe thoughts, how they move, how they forme themſelves, and put forth themſelves towards us, and the manifeſtation of them to us.</p>
               <p n="1">1. They are thoughts that delightfully reflect on themſelves; God takes a great deale of pleaſure in his own gracious thoughts to poore ſinners. <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.9. God is ſaid there <hi>to delight to doe us good.</hi> And <hi>Micah</hi> 7.18. <hi>Who is a God like thee, that pardoneth ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, and paſſeth by tranſgreſſion? he keepeth not anger for ever, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he delighteth in mercy.</hi> Though mercy ſeemes moſt to concerne us, yet God is joyed in his own thoughts of mercy. Wee may be ſad at ſomething in the beſt thoughts we thinke, for ſome mixture of ſin or vanitie in them: but Gods thoughts are ſo excellent like himſelfe, that he rejoyceth in them as in himſelfe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Theſe thoughts delight in minding the good of poore ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and ſo conſequently take delight that poore ſinners ſhould be the better for them. So in the ſaid two places of <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.9. <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cah</hi> 7.18. The precious ſtones, with the names of the Tribes in them on <hi>Aarons</hi> breaſt, ſignifie how Chriſt carries ſinners in the thoughts, and affections of his heart.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They are compaſſionate-relenting thoughts (if I may ſo ſay) over a poore ſinner that God hath wounded in the heart for ſinne, and is now complaining of his ſinne. <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.18. <hi>I have ſurely heard</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>Ephraim bemoaning himſelfe thus: [Thou haſt cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſed mee, and I was chaſtiſed</hi> (that is, I felt it) <hi>Turne thou mee, and I ſhall be turned, for thou art the Lord my God. Surely after that I was turned, I repented, and after that I was inſtructed, I ſmote upon my thigh; I was aſhamed, even confounded, becauſe I did beare the reproach of my youth.]</hi> Thus <hi>Ephraim:</hi> Now heare the Lords compaſſionate re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentings over theſe broken, repenting, praying hearts, <hi>ver.</hi> 20. [<hi>Is Ephraim</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>my deare ſonne? Is he a pleaſant childe? For ſince I ſpake againſt him, I doe earneſtly remember him ſtill. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my bowels are troubled for him.</hi> I <hi>will ſurely have mercy upon him, ſaith the Lord.</hi>] O admirable ſoule comforting place! God firſt
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:114123:11"/>
puts theſe repenting thoughts into a poore ſinner, and then how doth his heart melt with compaſſionating thoughts of mercy, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving to ſhew kindneſſe unto him?</p>
               <p n="4">4. They are patient opportunitie waiting thoughts, to doe a poore diſtreſſed ſoule good. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 30.18. <hi>And therefore will the Lord waite that he may be gracious unto you, and therefore will he be exalted to have mercy on you.</hi> (So in the <hi>Hebrew) For the Lord is a God of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or equitie, and uprightneſſe, bleſſed are all they that wait for him.</hi> See, the Lord ſets himſelfe forth as ſome good man, that is full of thoughts to doe ſome worthy worke, to ſhew ſome notable kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, who ſtands obſerving, and meditating, when and how he may take the beſt opportunitie to doe it. He ſets himſelfe like ſome Generall, in ſome high eminent place, to view when he may ſtep in to reſcue and relieve thoſe that are in danger and diſtreſſe. By which is held forth to us, that God is thinking kinde thoughts to us when he is not acting. And that he will not deferre a minute to ſhew us mercy, when his time is come.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Tender caring thoughts, for and to the meeke and broken heart. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 66.2. <hi>But to this man will I looke,</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>even to him that is of a poore and a contrite heart, and trembleth at my Word.</hi> God will not onely <hi>look on</hi> ſuch a one to have thoughts of pitie; but he will <hi>look to him,</hi> have a care to bind up his wounds. The <hi>poore</hi> that is deſpiſed of the world, God will look to, and ſhall be bleſſed in his thoughts, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. The <hi>contrite</hi> he will heale, <hi>Luk.</hi> 4.18. Thoſe that mourne for want of a ſacrifice (as they thinke) they bring a thing more acceptable then a ſacrifice unto God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. They that are affraid becauſe of the Word, they have here aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance that they are high in Gods thoughts.</p>
               <p n="6">6. To prevent any objection, that ſinne might hinder good things from us, he tells us that his thoughts are ſinne-ſurpaſſing thoughts; ſuper-abounding above all ſinnes. And indeed this ſeems ſometimes in ſome to ſuper-abound the Text, that ſaith, <hi>My thoughts are above your thoughts.</hi> For many times ſome poore ſinners cannot get their thoughts above their ſinnes, but their ſinnes doe maſter their thoughts; ſo that they cannot thinke but that their ſinnes ſurmount all that they can thinke. But now in this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar is ſhewed that Gods thoughts ſuper-abound all our ſinnes, and unworthineſſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.20. <hi>Where ſinne did abound, grace did much
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:114123:12"/>
more abound.</hi> And 1 <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 1.14. <hi>And the grace of our Lord was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing abundant;</hi> or as it is in the Greeke, <hi>did ſuper-abound.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. And laſtly, to number no more particulars; The thoughts of God are all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> thoughts for them that love him. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28. <hi>And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> know that all things worke together for good to them that love him.</hi> How doth the Apoſtle prove this? This he proves from Gods thoughts, <hi>verſ.</hi> 29. &amp;c. <hi>Whom he foreknew, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> predeſtinated to be confirmed to the image of his Sonne.</hi> Gods plot is no other then this, That <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> poore ſinner that loves him, ſhall fare no worſe (according to his meaſure) then his Sonne Chriſt Jeſus. Wee are apt to thinke we ſhall be made thus and thus miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable; but Chriſt is deſigned in Gods thoughts to be the platforme of our condition. Wee are apt to thinke, that the Devill, ſinne, world, and our own hearts conſpire our ruine. But Gods though<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> are that <hi>all,</hi> even <hi>all</hi> ſhall <hi>work together,</hi> ſhall cooperate, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bine together, <hi>to worke for our good.</hi> Whatſoever the evills of hell, and heart, and world may intend, yet Gods thoughts have plotted to bend all to this, and to further this method and event; <hi>That whom God did foreknow, them he predeſtinated, whom he predeſtinated, them he called, whom he called, them he juſtified, whom he juſtifies, than be glorifies.</hi> Nothing muſt intervene, invert, or ſubvert this order.</p>
               <p>Third uſe is to performe our dutie to this mercy.</p>
               <p n="1">1. To forſake our own thoughts, <hi>ver.</hi> 7. before the Text. That is, not to believe our own thoughts, oppoſing in the leaſt Gods thoughts.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To be ſure to thinke high enough, large enough of Gods thoughts of favour. If thou canſt tell, or canſt not tell what thy ſinnes are; be ſure to thinke that thy ſinnes are but finite, Gods thoughts of mercy infinite. So in the Text.</p>
               <p n="3">3. To draw neere to, to invocate and ſeek to the God of mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy, in the time of his offer of mercy, <hi>verſ.</hi> 6. Compare 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.2.</p>
               <p n="4">4. To waite for the diſpenſations and manifeſtations of the acts of Gods thought of mercy, ſo as the earth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> on the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens for raine, <hi>verſ.</hi> 10.</p>
               <p n="5">5. To look to God to make the expreſſions of the thoughts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> take your hearts, and make impreſſions upon them; as God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> makes the raine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to the earth. In this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 10. <hi>verſ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. And laſtly, to take heed the mean while of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> againſt and abuſing mercy, <hi>verſ.</hi> 7.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:114123:12"/>
               <head>GODS GRACIOUS EXPRESSIONS, Engaging himſelfe to them that accept of his GRACE.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>2 COR. 1.3, 4.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Bleſſed be God, even the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the Father of mercies, and the God of all Comfort; who comforteth us in all our tribulation, that wee may be able to comfort them which are in any trouble, by the comfort wherewith we our ſelves are comforted of God.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe words were ſpoken to them that not long before had been bad enough;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.9, 10, 11.</note> 
                  <hi>Know YEE not</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle to <hi>theſe) that the unrighteous ſhall not inherit the kingdome of God? Be not deceived, neither fornicators, nor Idolaters, nor adulterers, nor effeminate, nor abuſers of themſelves with mankinde, nor theeves, nor covetous, nor drunkards, nor revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, nor extortioners ſhall inherit the kingdome of God. AND S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>CH WERE SOME OF YO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>.</hi> But ſince they were waſhed. They <hi>are</hi> SUCH; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ee</hi> are <hi>WASHED.</hi> They were ſuch as had accepted of Gods gracious favor offered in Chriſt (though many of them very weakly, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.) and ſo now the Apoſtle ſpeaks to them as to <hi>Saints,</hi> and <hi>members of the Church</hi> at <hi>Corinth,</hi> ver. 1. And the Apoſtle includes himſelfe, as <hi>ver.</hi> 3. <hi>Peace from God O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R Father.</hi> And in the Text, <hi>O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R Lord Jeſus Chriſt. The God of all comfort, who comforteth <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> to the end to advance th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> converted <hi>Corinthians</hi> up into the ſame predicament and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:114123:13"/>
with him and <hi>Timothy.</hi> Though <hi>Paul</hi> &amp; <hi>Timothy</hi> be the <hi>primipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>es,</hi> the Captains and chief ſharers in that of the Text, and laid as a pattern afore the <hi>Corinthians.</hi> So that the Apoſtle means by <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi> in the Text, at leaſt ſuch as had received <hi>grace</hi> and favour, <hi>v.</hi> 2. were <hi>true</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ints, <hi>ver.</hi> 1. And ſutable he cuts out ſuch large portions, as were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> for Kings children, <hi>viz. peace,</hi> flowing from <hi>grace.</hi> And doth not onely bequeath great things to them there: But here in the Text, ſhews them a large firme deed of gift, of what God through Chriſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d beſtowed upon them. <hi>Bleſſed be God, even the Father of our Lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſus Chriſt,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Who comforteth us,</hi> &amp;c. as it is in the Text.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Doct.</note>
                  <hi>God is here ingaged to his people by many engagements, to be unto them all comfort.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here are two generalls to be explained.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. The comfort that God is to his.</item>
                  <item>2. The engagements upon God, to be this comfort.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Two things muſt be explained to open the firſt.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>That</hi> comfort is of God.</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>What</hi> that comfort is, from God.</item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>That</hi> comfort is from God. He is ſaid in the Text to be the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>d of Comfort.</hi> As <hi>Satan</hi> is ſaid to be the <hi>God of this world;</hi> And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>he <hi>Prince of the power of the ayre,</hi> and the <hi>Prince of darkneſſe;</hi> And is called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>THE Accuſer; <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, THE Temptor; <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, THE Wicked One;</hi> As being the cauſe at leaſt in part of all miſchiefe and miſery; So in a way of contrarietie and remedy, God is ſaid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ere to be <hi>The God of comfort.</hi> Againe as the world is ſaid by <hi>John</hi> to be <hi>a world of wickedneſſe;</hi> and by <hi>Solomons</hi> to be <hi>vanitie and vexation of ſpirit;</hi> And by the Saints <hi>a wilderneſſe, (Cant.</hi> 3.6.) in which is nothing but want, and deſolateneſſe, and diſconſolateneſſe; ſo in contrarietie and for remedy againſt all this, God is ſaid here, to be the <hi>God of comfort.</hi> Againe as death is ſaid to be (<hi>Job</hi> 18.14.) <hi>The King of Terrours,</hi> which is that which oft caſts a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ddain ſhadow, a thick darkneſſe upon all the glory of meer-mens worldly injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: ſo in contrarietie, and for remedy of all, it is ſaid here, <hi>God is the God of comfort.</hi> On the other ſide, As a King is called by great titles, is inveſted with great power, clothed with great ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, compaſſed with great wealth, and all manner of proſperitie, in importing how able he is to make his Queene, Children, Allies, favourites, &amp;c. outwardly happie; So in oppoſition to, and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendencie
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:114123:13"/>
above all, God is here ſaid to be <hi>the God of comfort,</hi> who (elſewhere) is called <hi>the King of Kings.</hi> And becauſe Dan. 2.37. Hoſ. 10, 8. ſome earthly kings have proudly taken or received that title of <hi>King of kings:</hi> therefore God in Chriſt is ſaid to be the <hi>King of kings, and Lord of lords, the onely Potentate.</hi> Importing, that what ever comforts Kings and Princes may ſeem to have, or hold forth to men, they had them from this <hi>King of kings,</hi> who hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite more to beſtow, then all the kings of the earth put together; and to give them more effectually and bleſſedly. For God is not onely the Adminiſterer and Diſpencer of comfort, but the Author and maker of comfort. He <hi>creates peace,</hi> He <hi>creates joy.</hi> Yea leſs the matter of our comfort. Yea ſo, that a glympſe of his face, one beam of his Countenance is for the time, heaven upon earth; even as his preſence is the form of the glory of heaven.</p>
               <p>Secondly, To tell you <hi>what</hi> comfort is of God, two things muſt be explained.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The <hi>Quantitie.</hi> 2. The <hi>Quality</hi> of that comfort that is from God.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The <hi>Quantity</hi> of this comfort. 1. In <hi>number,</hi> the comforts from God are plural, many. It is not ſaid onely in the Text, <hi>mercie</hi> in the <hi>abſtract</hi> (whereas Exod. 34. it is in the <hi>concrete</hi> God is <hi>mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull</hi>) but mercy is in the <hi>plurall,</hi> and not in the ſingular. So alſo Rom. 12.1. God knowing we have many miſeries, he counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poiſeth, ballanceth all with this, that he hath many mercies. As Iſa. 55. He ſpeaks of <hi>multiplying pardons,</hi> becauſe of our many ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; and of <hi>loving kindneſſes</hi> oft in the Pſalmes, becauſe of our many <hi>wants;</hi> ſo here of <hi>mercies,</hi> becauſe of our many miſeries, many exigencies to need pity.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In <hi>kind,</hi> great in the <hi>quantity</hi> of comfort from God. It is ſaid here, God is <hi>the God of all comfort;</hi> therefore of all <hi>kindes</hi> of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort that can truly be ſaid to be comfort. If there be any comfort in husband, wife, friend, c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ild, it is becauſe there is the image or impreſſe of God there. If there be any comfort in an ordinance, it is becauſe God comes in. If any comfort in creatures, it is as it is looked upon as coming from God, and leading us to God. That as we obſerve God to ſerve our turnes in them, we likewiſe by them ſerve him As the Sun quickening and warming the Plants, it makes them ſhoot up towards it ſelf. As there is more comfort in a
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:114123:14"/>
friend oft-times then in his gift, and we delight more in ſerving our friend with a comodity, then in keeping of it: ſo there is more joy in God, and in ſerving him, then in all we receive, or doe, or can keep. And in a word, as the Sun is the Original of all light; ſo God that Sun, Pſal. 84. verſ. <hi>ult.</hi> is the original of all comfort.</p>
               <p n="3">3. In <hi>degrees</hi> great is the quantity of comfort that is from God. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> he be, as it is in the Text, <hi>The God of all comfort,</hi> then of all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of any comforts whatſoever, that are or may be communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from him to his people. And for inſtance, we have a glorious <hi>Gradual</hi> of Gods comforting in the Text.</p>
               <p>The firſt and loweſt degree that the comfort that is from God is <hi>efficacious</hi> and effectual comfort. Though we are in <hi>tribulation,</hi> yet (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>God comforteth us in all.</hi> Tribulation is a ſoarer degree of affliction, ſignifying <hi>threſhing,</hi> yet God comforts us in this, yea in the <hi>all of this.</hi> All the threſhing doth but beate the wheat out of the chaffe, and after by ſtrokes, or the flooring, makes it more bright. God makes his to <hi>glory in Tribulation,</hi> Rom. 5. And it follows at the heels of the Text, verſ. 5. <hi>As the ſufferings of Christ abound in us, ſo our conſolation alſo aboundeth by Christ.</hi> And the Pſalmiſt ſaith, Pſal. 94.19. <hi>In the multitude of my thoughts (that is of ſorrow) within me, thy comforts delight my ſoul.</hi> Afflictions ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times are the very matter of rejoycing, Matth. 10. <hi>When they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute you for my Names ſake, rejoyce and be exceeding glad, for great is your revvard.</hi> And the Apoſtles in the Acts, <hi>went avvay rejoycing from the Councel, that they vvere counted vvorthie to ſuffer for the name of Christ.</hi> Sometimes afflictions drive us more and more neere to God in prayer; And generally God is much with his Saints in the ordinance of chaſtiſement. Therefore it is ſaid, Pſ. 94.12. <hi>Bleſſed is the man vvhom thou doſt afflict, and teach out of thy Lavv.</hi> And Jam. 1. <hi>Count it all joy vvhen ye fall into diverſe temptations.</hi> This is no ſmall comfort, whoſe beams ſhall pierce through the thick dark cloud of our ſorrows; and whoſe influence ſhall ſoake through a world of trouble, to beget comfort in the midſt of the heart of this little earth, joy in ſorrows, and life in death: Our <hi>comforts</hi> ſhall more abound <hi>by</hi> Chriſt, then our <hi>ſufferings for</hi> Chriſt; beſides all that is to come. 2 Cor. 4. God is ſo effectual in his comforting, that he will comfort whom he will comfort. If the world count
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:114123:14"/>
it a reproach to be afflicted and perſecuted; yet <hi>the ſpirit of glorie</hi> (ſaith <hi>Peter) ſhall rest upon us the mean vvhile.</hi> And thus effectuall ſhall Gods comfort be in all tribulation. God doth not onely com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort on the mount of temptation, but in the valley of inward de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections; not onely under the rod as <hi>Paul,</hi> and the Apoſtles, but in the ſtocks, in the Lyons denne, in the fiery oven, &amp;c. Hebr. 11. As God gives us a ſtock, a ſoul of graces, againſt the body of ſin, ſo an army of comforts againſt all other diſcomforts. God will appear to be omnipotent in comforting, as well as in creating and preſerving.</p>
               <p>But ſecondly, and higher. This comfort from God is an <hi>appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended comfort.</hi> We ſhall not onely have comfort at a time, and not know it, (as Pſal. 22. The Pſalmiſt is deſſertion yet cryed <hi>my God</hi>) but we ſhall be comforted, and know we are comforted. So the Text, <hi>Chriſt will give us of his Spirit, that we may knovv the things that are given us of God.</hi> 1 Cor. 2.12. <hi>If his love paſſeth knovvledge,</hi> Eph. 3. yet he will cauſe us to <hi>feel it.</hi> Rom. 5. he will <hi>ſhed it into our hearts.</hi> As we feel the comfort of the Sun oft-times, when we cannot behold the brightneſſe of it, ſo it is in the apprehenſion of Gods love.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, yet higher. It is oft-times <hi>redundant comfort,</hi> ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abounding comfort; it ſhall be not onely <hi>good meaſure preſſed dovvn,</hi> for our uſe, but running over for others refreſhment. So in the Text. <hi>We ſhall be able to comfort others,</hi> our comfort ſhall not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fill our banks of deſires, but float the valley of ſaints round about us. As the Widdows oyle and meal, ſeeming but a little, fed her, and the Prophet too. As God comforted Chriſt in his ſufferings, ſo he us, (both Heb. 5.7.9.) So we from Chriſts comfort to us, comfort one another. We ſhall light one anothers candle, and mean while have never the leſſe our ſelves. The parent comforts the elder children, and they ſhall ſtill the younger.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, yet higher: It is <hi>experimental</hi> comfort. We ſhall not onely communicate our comforts to others, but we ſhall be able to tell the Saints that this and this is comfort. That this and that comfort hath wrought effectually upon us, and hath done the deed, in a time of diſtreſſe hath ſupported; We have not onely heard the receipt read to us, but we took it downe, and it wrought kindly. It cordialized the heart to purpoſe. They that know not the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolations
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:114123:15"/>
of God, ſlight them as nothing (as it is in Job. 15.11.) but we know what they are by inward feeling.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, Higher. It is <hi>ſtrong laſting</hi> comfort. It keeps oft-times long at an high pitch, at leaſt on its, or in communication to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: When the medicine is made, it doth not evaporate its ſpirits, and grow weak. It is not deadned by pouring it out of one veſſel, one heart into another. But the ſame comfort that comforted us, comforts others. The ſame plaiſter heals many ſores. The reverſion of heavenly comfort is as good at laſt, as at firſt.</p>
               <p>The ſame word, ſpirit, and ordinances; have comforted thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands above theſe 4000. years.</p>
               <p>Sixtly, Higher yet. God oft-times ſends in ſo much comfort as to make a ſoul to be in <hi>the high key of Hallelujahs:</hi> to make it mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie and bleſſe God for his comfort. So in the Text, <hi>Bleſſed be God</hi> &amp;c. <hi>that hath comforted us,</hi> &amp;c. God will not onely give us com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to live, but to joy in him. As the Sun gives forth not onely to make the plants grow, but to bloſſome. So God hatcheth up comfort unto the bloſſoming of joy, (<hi>Flores plantarum gaudia,</hi> Plin. Nat. Hiſt.) As flowers are the joy of Plants, ſo Joy the flower or bloſſomes of our graces, as deſires are the root. <hi>In God</hi> (faith the Pſalmiſt) <hi>we make our boast all the day long.</hi> God will ſweetly touch the heart-ſtrings with the finger of his Spirit, not onely to make them ſound with comfort, but to reſound and eccho praiſe, and make it become a Pſalmiſt. The world ſhall ring of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort <hi>Moſes, Deborah, Hannah, David, Elizabeth, Marie, Paul, Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las,</hi> &amp;c. had received. This heavenly ſire will break forth. God will delight his owne eare with his owne muſick. He will put joy and gladneſſe into the heart till it praiſe him.</p>
               <p>Thus the <hi>quantitie</hi> of comfort ſhall be like the <hi>manna. He that gathered little had no want, he that gathered much had no overplus,</hi> more then was uſefull.</p>
               <p>Secondly, For the <hi>qualitie</hi> of comfort, it is the <hi>comfort that is of God.</hi> And Gods comfort is like himſelf. The <hi>Worlds</hi> comfort is a <hi>lying</hi> comfort. The <hi>Divels</hi> comfort is a <hi>damnable flattering</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort. Yea the beſt comfort from things below are <hi>mixed,</hi> if not <hi>mudded.</hi> But the comfort that is from God, is in this like God, that as it is <hi>much,</hi> (as we have heard) ſo <hi>pure,</hi> and <hi>ſpiritual,</hi> it
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:114123:15"/>
reacheth to the ſoul and ſpirit of a man. A dram of this powder of pearle, <hi>aurum pota bile,</hi> this <hi>aqua Coeleſtis,</hi> this Chriſt communica<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted comfort, is more worth then an hundred weight of groſſe ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lunary comforts. A look of Chriſt on <hi>Peter,</hi> makes him mourne that he loved Chriſt no more. One glympſe of the transfigurati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſt, wrapps up the three diſciples as into the third hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. A touch of this loadſtone makes the heart forget all, and to move towards it. Forgeth all lines but that which immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tends to it. This comfort makes <hi>Dauid</hi> to deſpiſe come, and wine in compariſon, <hi>Pſal</hi> 4. This makes the Diſciples to deſpiſe all, with <hi>It is good to be here.</hi> A word of this from Chriſt to buffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Paul</hi> ſtilled him. A glance of God on <hi>Moſes,</hi> makes him glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious. In other comforts, <hi>in the midſt of laughter the heart is ſad,</hi> But this comfort makes glad, and addes no ſorrow. Thus of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort.</p>
               <p>Next of <hi>Gods engagement of himſelf to comfort his.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wee will note both the <hi>matter,</hi> and the <hi>method,</hi> of ſetting down theſe engagements here.</p>
               <p n="1">1. For the engagement conſidered in the <hi>matter,</hi> to take them in order of the Text; 1. He is <hi>God,</hi> as much as to ſay, he is <hi>good,</hi> He is the chief good; the more good in any thing, the more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municative it is of it ſelfe. God cannot be God but he muſt be <hi>good.</hi> He cannot be moſt good, but he muſt be moſt communicative of his goodneſſe; ſo that as ſoone as God was God, which was from all eternity, God laid up the <hi>Idea</hi> or plat-form of us in his thoughts to do us good: He conceived in himſelfe the model of our being, and well being; deſigned for us two worlds below, one naturall for our bodies, another ſpirituall for our ſoules, and one of Glory in the world to come, for ſoule and body joyntly: In this world to enjoy him mediately, by communication of himſelfe: in that to come, by beatificall viſions. This communication of himſelfe as he is <hi>good,</hi> is delicately touched by the Pſalmiſt, Pſal. 119. <hi>Thou art good, and doſt good:</hi> It is the impreſſion of Gods goodneſſe upon all the creation; <hi>Sun, Sea, Elements</hi> &amp;c. that makes them commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicative of comfort to man, How much more is God, infinitely good, communicative of his comfort. Therefore, 1. It is ſaid in the Text, <hi>He is the God of comfort,</hi> which ſets forth his goodneſſe. 2. That he comforteth us: Here is his communicativeneſſe; the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:114123:16"/>
reſult of all is this. Then God will ceaſe to be communicative of comfort to his, when he can ceaſe to be God, and not afore, <hi>He cauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his Sunne to ſhine upon the good and the bad,</hi> therefore he will ray forth beams of comfort on his Saints. But are not the Saints in want of comfort, when they oft and much cry for comfort? We anſwer, They want ſo much comfort as they deſire to have, but even then they have a ſaving degree of comfort, elſe they would deſpair, not poure out prayers: I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is ſome ſtock of comfort they turne and winde in prayer, to get more, as Pſal. 22.1. whiles hee cryed for Gods preſence, he had this comfort, Hee was his God: and vvhiles the Spouſe ſeems to have loſt Chriſt, ſhe enquires after him, calls him <hi>her reloved,</hi> Cant. 5. Thus of the firſt engagement.</p>
               <p n="2">2. He is the <hi>Father of our Lord Ieſus Christ:</hi> Here comes in the kin: And relations, though of the leaſt entitie, are of the greateſt ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacy: As Chriſt is the <hi>last man,</hi> (as the Apoſtle calls him, 1 Cor. 15.) The ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> is the <hi>everlaſting Father</hi> to all beleevers, Iſai. 9. ſo God is his Father, ſo in the text, yea as Chriſt is the repreſentative of us all that beleeve, ſo God is our Father in, and through Chriſt, being Chriſts Father: Therefore it is ſaid, <hi>Reckon your ſelves as you are in him,</hi> Rom. 6.11. And we are <hi>accepted in him,</hi> Epheſ. 1.6. And <hi>Co-heirs with him,</hi> Rom. 8. So as that God comforts Chriſt as he is the Father of Chriſt, Heb. 5. <hi>He heard him in that he feared,</hi> ſo God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts us in text, as younger brethren, Heb. 2. as his members, Eph. 4. Yea this union betweene Chriſt and us, is ſet forth, to bee ſo cloſe, and intimate, (Ioh. 14.20. Ioh. 17.22.) That we may boldly ſay, as long as God comforts Chriſt, he muſt needs comfort us that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve in Chriſt. If God will maintain his ſonnes titles, <hi>Lord, Ieſus, Christ,</hi> then he muſt comfort us, through him, hee muſt defend and ſuccour us under his <hi>Lordſhip,</hi> ſave us under his <hi>Ieſusſhip,</hi> and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noint us ſpiritually with the ſpirit, by his <hi>Chriſtſhip:</hi> Yea, Chriſts body now in heaven is an earneſt that we ſhall be there too, Ioh. 14.2.3. Can any relation be tenderer then that of a Father? Can any ſon be dearer to God then Chriſt? Can any bee nearer to Chriſt than we that beleeve, that are ſaid, We are ſo joyned to the Lord, that we are one ſpirit? How then can it be poſſible but that God ſhould have infinite bowels of love to Chriſt, and ſo to us in him? He hath no other to love as children, he hath none elſe to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow all his great eſtate upon.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:114123:16"/>3. Engagement. God is the <hi>Father of mercies,</hi> or as it is in the Greek, He is the Father of bowells of mercies: Not only the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour</hi> of mercies, but the <hi>Father</hi> of mercies; he gives all his gifts with a paternall affection. None of his gifts to any of his, are giftleſſe gifts.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Father of bowels,</hi> doth import that as a father is not a naturall father, if he looſe his bowels, ſo God muſt keep his bowells of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, as he will keep his relation of Father to his: And as a fathers bowells of mercies deſcend to the children of his Naturall bowells, ſo Gods compaſſion is to his: You ſee by how many titles our te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nure of mercies hold good: One while as we are ſervants to God or Chriſt our maſter, <hi>Truly I am thy ſervant,</hi> (ſaith <hi>David) I am thine, ſave me.</hi> Another while as a <hi>Wife</hi> to Chriſt Hoſ. 2. Another while as <hi>Children</hi> to God, and brethren to Chriſt: and ſo this Text, And adde to all, that if we ſhould faile, ſo as to undeſerve that God ſhould be called the Father of us as his children, yet this muſt ſtand firme, <hi>God is the Father of mercies,</hi> Namely, to pitty us as a Father doth the childe as it is Pſal. 103. And to ſpare us, and beare with us, as a <hi>Father doth a weak childe that ſerveth him</hi> as he can, though as a weak childe, as <hi>Malachy</hi> ſpeaks, chap. 3. verſ. 18. And he is the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Mercies, in the plurall, <hi>Numeroſa proles,</hi> Store of mercies. As God cannot be the Father of Chriſt (as Chriſt) alone, All be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers are included in him, and ſo is well pleaſed. It is not ſaid, <hi>with,</hi> but <hi>in him,</hi> Matth. 3. So he cannot be the Father of one mercy only, but of many, to have ſome for all, yea, many for every One, yet he that is rich in mercies cannot leave his children poor.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Engagement, It is his ſtile, title, deſcription, that hee is <hi>The God of all comfort:</hi> It is here ſpoken, as the definition of what hee is to us, therefore as eſſentiall to him. And the like is ſaid of him, Exod, 34. by way of a Royall Title, or Kingly ſtile, <hi>The Lord, the Lord God Iehovah, mercifull, gracious, long ſuffering, aboundant in goodneſſe,</hi> &amp;c. So that this of Gods comforting us, is one of the flowers in his crowne, and God muſt maintaine his ſoveraigne ſtile. How ſhall he be ſaid to be God, that is (as we ſhewed afore) infinite good, if not full with comfort, abounding towards us. And how a God of all comfort, if his people ſhall have none?</p>
               <p n="2">2. For the <hi>method</hi> of theſe engagements, in a word; The God of this comfort, 1. removes impediments that might hinder us
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:114123:17"/>
their minds from God, are not contented with glory. And the <hi>Saints beleeving in Chriſt,</hi> whiles they have ſought what was in the creature, and not God through the creature, have found nothing in any thing, or all things <hi>conjunctim</hi> or <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſim,</hi> ſeverally or conjunctively. Eccleſ. 2.1. to the 12. <hi>verſe</hi> King <hi>Solomon</hi> the <hi>great,</hi> in making the utmoſt of all creature comforts, could find nothing but <hi>vanitie, and vexation. Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> is an high and intellectuall delight, is, a while, a pleaſure to the mind; but unleſſe God comes in, it furfets the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and is a wearineſſe to the fleſh. Eccleſ. 12.12. Muſick is pleaſant to the eare, but unleſſe God comes in to cheere the heart it is nauſeous to a man Pſal. 137. And as experience tels us, being too long in the hearing may ſurfet the phantaſie with too oft playing the ſame leſſon. <hi>Odours</hi> are pleaſant to the ſmell, and ſome ſay the food of the Spirits of the Braine; but unleſſe God come in with health they ſuffocate that ſence, and cauſe faintings, and ſwownings. <hi>Food</hi> is pleaſant to the taſt; but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe God give in his bleſſing, it ſurfeits the ſtomacke.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In the midſt of laughter</hi> in all creature injoyments (ſaith <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon) the heart is ſad.</hi> Yea creature-joyes with out God are miſchiefes. <hi>Apparrel</hi> makes more proud then warme. <hi>Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> brings forth more tyrannicalneſſe than reformation. <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> becomes more arrogant then uſefull, <hi>Wine</hi> more making mad than merry. The <hi>table</hi> is become a ſnare. As it is ſaid of wiſdome that all the creatures were inquired of; a generall counſell of all the world was called; the creation met in conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, to give in their anſwer every creature for himſelfe, whither wiſdome was in this, or that, or the other: they all anſwered no. Job 28.12. &amp;c. And ſo it may be ſaid of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort; if all the world be called to its Anſwer, it cannot ſay con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctively or diviſively that comfort is there, without God. The <hi>Sea</hi> anſwers, that it is not in mee, I am a devourer, and doe make many a Merchant ſad. The heavens anſwer it is not in mee. For unleſſe God helpe mee, I cauſe barrenneſſe, (<hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.). And the <hi>ſonnes of men</hi> confeſſe (if they will ſpeake the truth) that they are as Jobs friends, without God, miſerable comforters. They can ſee one miſerable, and ſay this and that, but without the incomes of God cannot comfort. One man
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:114123:17"/>
is contented with a little. why? God is there. Another is not contented with much. Why? God is not there. A little that a righteous man hath (ſaith <hi>Solomon</hi>) is better than great revenues of the wicked. For God is the comfort in every creature com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, and God makes every creature to give down his comfort.</p>
               <p n="1">1. God <hi>is the comfort</hi> in every creature. It is the word, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, or inſtitution of God, that makes bread to be meanes of life to us, <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Hee makes the <hi>creature to give downe</hi> his comfort that is in him: <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.21. &amp;c. <hi>I will (ſaith the Lord) in that day heare the heavens, and they ſhall heare the earth, and earth ſhall heare the corne and the wine, and the oyle, and they ſhall hear Jezreel.</hi> And all this God will do for his, becauſe <hi>hee will make a covenant with them, and betreth them to himſelfe.</hi> ver. 18. All ſhall be paid downe as part of their dowrie as part of that all which is theirs in Chriſt Jeſus 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.21. Therefore why doe we travell over creature comforts without God our convoy? Yea why do wee travell to creature comforts to find them without God? Can the Bee finde any thing in the flower without beames and drops of heaven firſt fall upon them. So vaine is our endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to preſſe out and diſtill any ſpirits of comfort out of crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, without Gods influence or impreſſions firſt falling upon them. We thinke becauſe God comming in with creatures they ſometime comfort, that therefore the creatures themſelves do comfort. But if a divine ordinance doth not alwayes quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, but onely when God comes in, as experience tells us, much leſſe can earthly creatures comfort without God giving in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, in, and through them.</p>
               <p>Againe, we lament the loſſe of ſuch, and ſuch a creature, as conceiving, that we have much loſſe of comfort thereby. But I ſhould rather thinke that God taking them away, that if they were preſent they ſhould not comfort, nor would God come in through them to make them comfort, but that God is now upon another deſigne; namely, to give in more comfort ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way, as either by and in providentiall diſpenſations of affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, or in inſtituted ordinances of Word and Sacraments, or immediately by himſelfe in communication of his Spirit. Juſt as when an earthquake ſtops the ſprings on this ſide the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:114123:18"/>
yee may expect them to breake out in ſome other place.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ob.</hi> If creatures of themſelves cannot comfort without God comming in; how doe carnall men that have no intereſt in God rejoyce in them?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> 1. Some flatter themſelves that they have God; and argue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> from their having worldly comforts, that therefore God loves them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Others feare they have not God, and ſo in the midſt of <hi>laughter their heart is ſad.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Others have neither of thoſe apprehenſions, but are Atheiſticall, and ſo their joy is but flaſhes, <hi>as the crackling of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ornes under the pot.</hi> (As <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks.)</p>
               <p>Therefore ſtill the truth ſtands firme, without God no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in creatures. And therefore our ſureſt way is to croſſe our common courſe; namely, inſtead of going to creatures to finde God, to goe to God firſt, to have the creatures, and to finde comfort in it. To fetch every mercy warmed from the hand of God.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That though the Saints may need comfort, yea, and from creatures too, yet God hath reſerved to himſelfe to be the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ine and diſpenſer of all comfort to them through every thing to keepe them in a dependance upon them. <hi>Bleſſed be God</hi> (ſaith the text) <hi>the God of all comfort, that hath comforted us in all our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ibulations,</hi> that he may comfort us, and comfort us, that wee may owne him the author of comfort, in bleſſing him for it; and ſo all our dependence on him. God keeps the locke and key of all comforts, we muſt be beholding to him for all. <hi>Elijah</hi> muſt pray to God to unlock the <hi>clouds</hi> that it raine. The Church <hi>Act.</hi> 12. pray to God to unlock the <hi>priſon</hi> doores to let out <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> The Spouſe prayes <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.4. that God would unlock her <hi>heart,</hi> that it might be unchained and forced to run after him. Therefore it is a maine ſpirituall duty in all our injoyments, more to conſider the <hi>motions of our hearts towards God,</hi> through all comforts, then to looke upon the <hi>movings of comforts towards us.</hi> It is good to ſee the beames of divine favour to ſhine a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry upon all the flouds of our comforts; but better to ſee the ſtreames of them to carry us afloat to the ocean of all, God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:114123:18"/>
This the maine of all on our part, and this the great thing God lookes after; as a father more looks at the childs affections towards him, then upon what he layes out upon him. Therefore let us aime at that moſt, that God moſt looks at. We ſee all the creation of plants manifeſt their dependence on the drops and beams of heaven by ſhooting up towards heaven. Grace the activeſt thing under God, muſt needs have a ſtronger inſtinct to aſcend to that from whence it came. A ſure ſigne mercyes come from heaven, by ſpeciall diſpenſations of favour when they exhale and draw us up to a tendency thitherward, when wee imbrace the creatures, though as God in them, we imbrace but the <hi>hand</hi> of God, wee kiſſe his hand; but when by them wee aſcend up to conſider God as better then all, wee ſtroke his <hi>face,</hi> and <hi>kiſſe his mouth</hi> that bids the creatures go ſerve us, &amp; ſmiled upon us the while. And farre greater is our ſweet <hi>communion with the giver,</hi> then our <hi>poſſeſſion of the gift,</hi> wee forget our letters and tokens while wee imbrace our divine husband himſelfe. Anſwer wee then to Gods deſigne. Hee hath ſet all in a dependance on him, as the lines and circle to a Center. Therefore for all wee <hi>would</hi> have, yea for all that <hi>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready wee now</hi> have, to be comforts to us: go to god for them, and ſo <hi>accepta referre,</hi> to render back all to God againe, in away of prayſe. Bleſſe him for all, as it is in the Text. Let a prayer and a praiſe as it were hemme and compaſſe in God, given in through the particular mercy. Take in all our mercyes as ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comodations to further us in our journy homewards towards God. Let us delight more in <hi>parting</hi> with mercyes to <hi>ſerve God,</hi> our freind, then in <hi>keeping</hi> them to <hi>ſerve our ſelves,</hi> we can doe ſo for men, much more then let us doe ſo for God.</p>
               <p>In every thing give thankes <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.6. Let God have an <hi>exciſe</hi> out of all. About all things wee injoy, fetch as many errands to Court as you can, two at leaſt <hi>Viz,</hi> of prayer and prayſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning every particular. Mind this ſtill, that all that God doth is to mind thee of thy dependance. When <hi>Adam</hi> wanted nothing, God gave him a command and a <hi>threat</hi> to mind him of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendence. When he left his dependence on God in Paradiſe, he loſt all. So did the very <hi>Angells</hi> in the heaven of glory. As ſoone as they ſlacked their dependence on God, there they
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:114123:19"/>
fell. How much more ſhould wee mind our dependence, which is hourly and minutely. And therefore let us conclude that when God, upon ſight of our too fond ſetting our hearts upon creature-comforts withdrawes them from us, it is that wee might ſue them out upon our dependence: that wee might take a new ſtate from the <hi>chiefe Lord:</hi> and not gather them up as from the earth, as taking our tenour from the <hi>meane Lord</hi> yea when God afflicts it is that wee ſhould goe to him to bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ruted with comfort.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That comfort is given to us beleevers, that wee might with that, comfort others. So the text and wee muſt be like God, that communicates that comfort that is in him. Thus at once we can have comfort, and tell where we had it, to draw others to goe immediately to God. This doth nothing diminiſh our own comfort. But as a candle lighting many, ſhines rather more then leſſe it ſelfe the meane while, our comfort if truely <hi>good,</hi> is, will be communicative of it ſelfe. It is a muddie-poole, not a quick ſpring, that runnes not over, wee are a myſticall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, therefore our ſpirituall blood and ſpirits, and warmth muſt be in common.</p>
               <p>We talke oft of the ſweet of communion of Saints. Feaſt take, feaſt make, and wee get by this feaſting others ſoules with our ſpirituall comforts. The very telling of the ſtory of the manner how wee were comforted, is a chewing the cud and brings up the ſweet of our comfort upon our palates afreſh. But in the application, and preſſing of it upon the hearts of others, wee heate and warme our owne hearts and ſpirits. Wee rubbe the ſpices and make them ſmell more fragrant. Yea God is as well ſeen in his ſtreames of comfort running through the ground of our hearts, to anothers heart, as in running into our hearts at firſt. Therefore we having the firſt handſale, the firſt fruits, let us communicate. The wicked compaſſe Sea and Land to make proſelytes for the Devill, therfore let us much more for God: eſpecially conſidering Gods end, he gave thee comfort for that end. Every thing is moſt eminent in its operations when it is applyed to its end, and utmoſt end. As the ſun in its fulleſt ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, the inſtrument for the fulleſt muſick. Our comfort is moſt glorious, and God is moſt glorified, the more it comforts o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:114123:19"/>
as well as our ſelves. Its the fame of a river that it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſeth at ſuch a fountaine, &amp; runs ſo many hundred miles fructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies the vallies, and adornes the country as it goes, and then at length falls into the Ocean. As of <hi>Iordan,</hi> And <hi>Danube.</hi> So it is the honour of ſpirituall comforts to doe likewiſe in mens hearts.</p>
               <p n="4">4 That the excellenteſt comfort, and way of comforting is to comfort from experience, God comforts with the comfort he hath himſelfe, but of himſelfe, therefore ſo ſhould we, others from that we have from him, ſo the Text. Therefore the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle commends <hi>experience, Rom.</hi> 5 Experimentall comfort is like a medicine with a <hi>probatum eſt,</hi> that hath been proved to be effectuall. Experimentall comfort is like the Nurſe warming the milke or pappe in her owne mouth, before ſhe puts it into the childs.</p>
               <p>This layes a great ingagement upon a diſconſolate ſoule, to argue thus with himſelf, when he heares anothers experimentall comforts: <q>It is in the ſame God, the ſame word, the ſame Spirit, the ſame conſiderations that comforted him that now ſpeakes to me and he was the ſame in every reſpect as I was <hi>(aut ſumus aut fuimus, vel poſſumus eſſe quod hic eſt)</hi> why there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhould it not comfort me alſo?</q> why ſhould not I truſt God as well as another? where or when hath God excluded me from comfort more then him? Therefore oh yee comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Chriſtians draw forth your experimentall comforts, and ſerve them in to others. It is excellent to be an <hi>Empirick</hi> in ſpirituall <hi>phyſicking,</hi> as <hi>David</hi> ſpeakes, <hi>Come I will tell you what the Lord hath done for my ſoule.</hi> Waters running through mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralls as Brimſtone. Alum, &amp;c. have more ſtrength in them for a phyſicall uſe: ſo comfort is more fitted for men of like frailty with us, and takes more with them when they have firſt runne thorow our hearts, and have beene ſoaked in our experience, and ſo communicated with a ſtrong ſtreame of compaſſions, ſupplications and ſympatheticall conſent of ſpirits. Something for this lyes in our likeneſſe with them: ſomething in our ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and ſo are more feelingly wrought upon, when ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alls are communicated in a ſenſible way. Therefore <hi>examples</hi> oft worke more upon us then rules, but the maine thing for it lyes in Gods <hi>Inſtitution, and appointment,</hi> and therefore a divine
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:114123:20"/>
bleſſing goes along with it. God will alſo have the elder Chriſtian to be an executor of Chriſts teſtament of comfort to the younger: to exerciſe his graces and to keepe us all inu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion one with another. <hi>Thus of inſtructions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5 See wee be Gods people, ſet wee be his, that we may freely take this comfort to our ſelves.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtle deſcribes theſe to whom he writes, 1 Cor. 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. to be ſuch as are <hi>called to be ſaints,</hi> and <hi>ſanctified in Chriſt Ieſus.</hi> Theſe import three things. 1 The <hi>Qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of them that are Gods people, namely they are <hi>Saints,</hi> they are holy; they are of unholy made holy, holy in <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation,</hi> thats their common rode, and courſe of life. <hi>Titus</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.12. And holy in <hi>heart:</hi> that the <hi>complexion</hi> and temper of their hearts. Their hearts <hi>are purified by faith.</hi> Act. 15.9.2. The inſtrumentall meanes: <hi>called to be Saints.</hi> As the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>yee are not called to uncleanneſſe, but to holineſſe.</hi> They have heard a voyce in the <hi>eare,</hi> and a voyce at <hi>heart</hi> that have called them away from their former corrupt converſation, yea called them from their corrupt ſelves, from their corrupt condition, into that which is holy; from the world, to looke towards hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; from ſin, to Chriſt. So that they leave all rather then Chriſt, as the Apoſtles did, at Chriſts call. That is by the call of the word and holy Spirit, they could be ready to part with all ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then to part with Chriſt, and ſo we fall upon the third thing the <hi>principall meanes</hi> of their Saint-ſhip; namely ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in <hi>Chriſt Ieſus:</hi> not ſanctified or made pure only <hi>by Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> by his word and Spirit, but in <hi>Chriſt Ieſus.</hi> They are u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ed to Chriſt, looke upon themſelves in <hi>Chriſt.</hi> They reckon themſelves (as Rom. 6.11.) dead to ſinne in Chriſt, and alive to God in Chriſt. All their conſideration is to be <hi>found in him not having their owne righteouſneſſe, but the righteouſneſſe, which is th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ough faith of Chriſt.</hi> They behold Chriſt making a glorious change, Iſa. 53, 2 Cor. 5. <hi>ult. He was made ſinne for us, upon him the iniquities of us all were layd,</hi> that we might be <hi>made the righteouſneſſe of God:</hi> So that thoſe that are thus Gods people, they live as none of their owne, but as Gods for the generall of their lives. 1 Cor. 6.19, 20. 2 Cor. 5.15. Now thoſe that can with a good conſcience plead their <hi>ſincerity</hi> in theſe things;
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:114123:20"/>
though not their <hi>integrity</hi> or perfection take yee the ſweet com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts of this doctrine to your ſelves. God is the fountaine: ſo the text. <hi>The father of mercyes,</hi> Chriſt the Channel, ſo the text, the <hi>father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Say not who ſhall aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend up to heaven, to bring God or Chriſt downe thence; God is with thee, united to thee, in Chriſt Jeſus. Be not as <hi>Hagar</hi> to pine for thirſt for want of ſight of a well at hand. Be not as under <hi>Hagar,</hi> that is the Law, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. <hi>thou art not under the Law, but under grace:</hi> Rom. 6. Thou haſt the <hi>God of all comfort</hi> to be thine, by many engagements as hath beene clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to thee out of the text, and doctrine. Hee is the <hi>God of all comfort,</hi> it is his nature. He is the <hi>father of Chriſt,</hi> who is thy ſaviour, redeemer, and thine husband. He is the <hi>father of mercyes</hi> therefore of pitie to thee, that art one of the miſerable ones: <hi>He comforteth in all tribulation;</hi> therefore he is wonted to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort: yea till thou haſt enough to overflow to others, <hi>to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort them.</hi> Of all which wee ſpake in the explication; now rubbe and chaſe this ſuppling Oyle of gladneſſe upon thy ſoare ſoule.</p>
               <p>Hee is <hi>God;</hi> therefore good. Fully good; infinite in good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Freely good becauſe the firſt good. Therfore exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly communicative of goodneſſe; as in the creation ſo in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation.</p>
               <p>Hee creates <hi>peace,</hi> he creates <hi>a clean heart.</hi> He is a ſunne. Pſal. 84. Therefore muſt communicate himſelfe by beames.</p>
               <p>He is the <hi>Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> As God is the father of man-kind in the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> in a naturall way. <hi>Luk.</hi> 3. <hi>ult.</hi> So he is the father of beleevers, in and through Chriſt the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> in a <hi>ſpirituall</hi> way, ſo the text. The meaning is this: As ſure as God is united to Chriſt, ſo hee is to beleevers <hi>Joh.</hi> 14 20. <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.22. As ſure as God loves Chriſt. <hi>Mat.</hi> 3. <hi>ult.</hi> So ſure God loves thoſe in him. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.6. As ſure as God loves Chriſt as his ſunne; So Chriſt loves beleevers, called his children. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.9.</p>
               <p>Hee is the <hi>father of mercies</hi> wee are not ſo prone to bee fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of Children, as God is to be father of mercyes. Hee had not ſuffered his to have been miſerable, but to the intent to bee more glorious in his mercy. <hi>Hee concluded all</hi> (ſaith the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle)
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:114123:21"/>
                  <hi>in unbeleife that he might have mercy upon all.</hi> And then its preſently added, <hi>O the depth of the riches both of the wiſdome, and knowledg of God!</hi> Rom. 11.32.33.</p>
               <p>And hee is the God of <hi>all</hi> conſolation, therefore of <hi>ſome</hi> to ſome.</p>
               <p>And he <hi>comforteth us.</hi> It is his antient wont to comfort, and hee will not looſe his wont. With God is no ſhadow of change, no eclipſing of his beames, and he ſo inlightens be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers as ſtarres, that they ſhine upon things below. He will give comfort to them, and for a witneſſe of it they ſhall be able to comfort others. They ſhall ſee their own comfort was good, in that it takes with others. Yea, ſo comforted, that they ſhall indite a praiſe to God for it. <hi>Bleſſed be God that comforteth us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore, O ye that have ſeen your claime to this comfort, take it to you, graſp it; doe not let every diſtemper, melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly &amp;c. baffle you of your comfort. Doe as <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 42. <hi>ult.</hi> &amp; <hi>Pſal.</hi> 43. <hi>ult. Why</hi> the ſoule, and <hi>Wherefore</hi> the ſoule, examine it upon interrogatories, convince it with Quaeries, <hi>Why art thou caſt down O my ſoule? and why art thou diſquieted within me? Hope thou in God, for I ſhall yet praiſe him, who is the health of my countenance, and my God.</hi> As long as we have God, the God of all comfort to be ours, by as good intereſt as others had him on earth, that are now in heaven, why ſhould we be caſt down? What can ill us, wherein God cannot, or will not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort us, who is the God of all comfort, that comforteth in all tribulation? The conſideration of this Text, and Doctrine, and our intereſt in it, is enough to reſolve, and cleare all doubts. As whether we may cry to him in prayer in times of miſery?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw. He is the Father of mercies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whether we may approach near him after reciduations, and backſlidings into ſin? <hi>Anſw. He is the Father of mercies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whether we ſhall not ſinck in any condition, for want of comfort enough? <hi>Anſw. He is the God of all comfort, that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>orteth in all tribulation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If we fear this affliction, or that affliction; as one cryes, O I do not know how I ſhould indure poverty: another moanes, O how ſhall I encounter with the <hi>feare of death?</hi> The anſwer here is full to all caſes. <hi>God is the God of all comfort, Father of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies,</hi>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:114123:21"/>
in the plurall, <hi>and comforteth his in all tribulation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ob.</hi> But God is <hi>juſt</hi> too?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> And this is a comfort to a beleever, that layes hold on his free mercy, 1. <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.9. <hi>If we confeſſe our ſins, he is faithfull, and</hi> JUST <hi>to forgive us our ſins, and to cleanſe us from all unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi> And 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.6. <hi>It is a</hi> RIGHTEOUS, <hi>or juſt thing with God to recompence tribulation to them that trouble you, and to you who are troubled, reſt with us, &amp;c.</hi> So that Gods <hi>Juſtice</hi> is a friend to beleevers, againſt <hi>ſins</hi> and <hi>afflictions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ob.</hi> But God is a God of purity, that cannot indure iniquity, and of power to cruſh us for it in our afflictions?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Gods goodneſſe is the <hi>Complexion</hi> of his nature, and the perfection of all his Attributes: and therefore as he is prone to comfort, ſo by reaſon of his <hi>purity,</hi> he is <hi>pure</hi> in his comfort: and by reaſon of his <hi>power,</hi> he is <hi>powerfull</hi> in his comforts. Yea, and he hints to us, that it is more ſutable to his nature, and more anſwerable to his direct deſigne, <hi>to ſave and comfort,</hi> then to <hi>condemn</hi> and deſtroy his creature, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.16, 17. <hi>God ſo loved the world, that he gave his onely begotten ſon, that whoſoever belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth in him ſhould not periſh, but have everlaſting life. For God ſent not his ſon into the world, to condemn the world, but that the world through him might be ſaved.</hi> And <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.13. <hi>Mercy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyceth againſt judgement.</hi> Say thou then as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 77.16. <hi>My fleſh faileth, and my heart faileth, but God is the ſtrength of my heart, and my portion for ever.</hi> For ſurely Gods deſign is to make his child like himſelf, (in as much as he is willing to communicate him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe) to make him full of comfort, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.11. Therefore he bids us ſo oft to rejoyce, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4 4. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Therefore whereas we cry out for want of comfort, we have juſt cauſe rather to cry out againſt our ſelves, that wee receive not in that comfort God holds out unto us. For what by paſſion, and what by indiſcretion wee are like <hi>Rachel that wept and would not be comforted. In quietneſſe and confidence is our veſt and ſafety. And the joy of the Lord ſhall be our ſtrength.</hi> If our faith of adherence doth but work kindly in cleaving to Chriſt, that's comfort. Every thing is in a good eſtate in its own center. If the Lord keeps us from deſpaire, and puts us in hope of comfort, that is alſo a comfort.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:114123:22"/>
                  <hi>Ob.</hi> We ſay we have no comfort, becauſe we feele it not within, ſee it not work outwardly.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> But we may be rich, though wee doe not alwayes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ight or poyſe the bagges, or make them jingle, or ſee the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney powred forth. To have them in poſſeſſion is the richneſſe of our condition. We have life and reaſon when we are (as we lay) dead aſleep. To miſſe comfort is a ſign we had comfort. And Chriſt ſaith, <hi>our joy ſhall remain,</hi> Joh. 15.11. though our ſight and ſenſe of it doth not alwaies appeare. It is a ſigne there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſome water of joy in the pumpe of our deſires, while wee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>mpe for more.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ob:</hi> But you will ſay you have no joy, and therefore you doubt whether you have Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> But we ſay, a wife is a wife by vertue of her Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant in marriage, even then when ſhe is melancholy. And joy may glorifie and beautifie our ſpirits more; but to beleeve in God through Chriſt, when we have no actuall joy, doth more glorifie and honour God. This ſhews more pure faith, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.10. to truſt God without the <hi>pawne</hi> of ſenſe and feeling.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ob.</hi> Thou ſayeſt thou goeſt mourning from day to day for comfort, and canſt not attain unto it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Wee tell thee, ſuch deſires of comfort, they argue grace, as myſts doe quick fountaines where they are thickeſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. <hi>Bleſſed are they that mourn, bleſſed are they that hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and thirſt for righteouſneſſe.</hi> It's more actuall comfort to be deſirous of a mercy and think we have it not, then to know we have it, and to be glutted with it, or careleſſe of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ob.</hi> But thou wilt ſay thou haſt waited long for comfort, and yet haſt it not to thy content.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> We tell thee, it will be double in meaſure and ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe when it comes, <hi>A deſire fulfilled after a long deferring, is</hi> (ſaith Solomon) <hi>a tree of life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> But thou querieſt what ſhalt thou doe the while?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An.</hi> Wee tell thee, 1 God ſupports thee the while: and that is great comfort. 2 Thou ſhalt have communion with God in ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>king and waiting; and that alſo is a great comfort. 3 Thou ſhalt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ave ſo much of the oyle of gladneſſe, as to glib the wheels of thy ſoule to carry thee on to any heavenly journey till thou ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> at glory. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:114123:22"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
